Guide to the Oregon Hops and Brewing Archives Oral History Collection 2014-2017
Oregon State University Libraries, Special Collections and Archives Research Center
Dave Takush is the head cider maker at 2 Towns Ciderhouse in Corvallis, Oregon. He was born and raised in North Corvallis, surrounded by acres of grass fields and farmland. Takush has always been interested in science classes and cooking, so after graduating from Crescent Valley High School he studied Food Science and Technology at Oregon State University, specifically focusing on Fermentation Science and Oenology (B.S. 2007, M.S. 2009). He worked briefly as a winemaker in Eugene before he and friends Lee Larsen and Aaron Sarnoff-Wood started 2 Towns Ciderhouse in 2010.
Gillian Tobin is the Events and Marketing Coordinator at Mazama Brewing in Corvallis, Oregon. She was born in Colorado, but spent most of her childhood in Albany, Oregon. She moved to Eugene to attend the University of Oregon in 2006, earning her B.A. in Journalism and Communications in 2010. In 2008 she studied Italian language and literature at the Universita per Strainieri di Perugia. She worked for Hotel Deluxe in Portland from 2010 to 2013 before returning to Corvallis to begin working at the family brewery. In 2014 she began studying Graphic Design at Linn-Benton Community College, earning her Associate of Arts and Sciences in 2016.
Kathy Tobin is a co-founder and manager at Mazama Brewing in Corvallis, Oregon. She was born and raised in Michigan, and earned her B.S. in Electrical and Electronics Engineering from Michigan Technological University in 1983; while in college she was a member of the Blue Key Society and Eta Kappa Nu. She attended the Northwestern University Kellogg School of Management from 1994 to 1995, earning an Executive M.B.A. from the Executive Development Program. She returned to school in 2004 and earned a diploma from the Entrepreneurship Development Program at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology Sloan School of Management. After living in Colorado, Tobin moved to Corvallis and in 1998 took a position at Agilent Technologies as a Business Unit manager; she was there through 2002, when she left to take a position as a Vice President and General Manager at Hewlett-Packard. She was there until 2013, when she left to start Mazama Brewing with her husband Jeff.
Jeff Tobin is the co-founder and brewer at Mazama Brewing in Corvallis, Oregon. He born in West Branch, Michigan. He came from a very musical family, and played the trumpet for many years; he also loved science and math. Tobin went to college in 1979 at the Michigan Technological University, initially intending to become a sound engineer; he studied Electrical Engineering (B.S. 1983). He and his wife Kathy moved to Burlington, Vermont, where they began to home brew regularly. Tobin worked at IBM in Vermont before moving to Colorado in the 1980s, where he and his wife Kathy had two children. His family moved to Corvallis for jobs at Hewlett-Packard, where he worked as a Design Engineer until 2000. He worked at Agilent Technologies 2000 to 2005, Avago 2005 to 2006, and Marvell Semiconductor from 2006 to 2013. He and Kathy opened Mazama Brewing in 2012, where they use many recipes developed over their 24 years of home brewing.
Shaun Townsend is the senior researcher leading Oregon State University’s Aroma Hop Breeding Program. Townsend grew up in Central Illinois. He attended Montana State University, obtaining a B.S. in 1988 in Agronomy and a M.S. in Agronomy Plant Breeding and Forage Production in 1990. He received his Ph.D. in Agronomy Plant Breeding and Genetics in 1998 at New Mexico State University. Townsend began his work in Corvallis working with John Henning in the USDA-ARS hop breeding program; in 2010 he assumed responsibility for a new aroma hop breeding program in the OSU Department of Crop and Soil Science.
Don Weathers is a second-generation hop grower in the Willamette Valley. He was born in Salem and lived around the state on various family-owned farms. Weathers married Rosalie Kerr, who was also from a hop family, in 1958 and the couple had 6 children. The Weathers' farm was one of the test locations for growing the Cascade hop in the 1960s. The Weathers' land holdings expanded both in size in geography, most of the family's farms are now run by his children and grandchildren.
Kurt and Rob Widmer launched Widmer Brothers in 1984. Kurt graduated with a degree in psychology from the University of Oregon in 1978, then moved to Germany to work for a pharmaceutical company, registering foreign-made drugs for sale in the German market. His younger brother Rob studied business at Oregon State University in the early 1980s. The Craft Brew Alliance was formed in 2008 through a merger of Redhook Brewery and Widmer; at that time, the two companies sold stakes to Anheuser-Busch in exchange for access to a nationwide network of wholesalers. In 2015, Kurt Wider announced he would retire as CEO of the Craft Brew Alliance.
Dave Wills is the owner of Freshops, Oregon Trail Brewery, and Dave's Christmas Trees. Wills grew up in Santa Paula, California, and studied Agriculture at a junior college before transferring to Oregon State University (B.S. 1980). His early interest in home brewing was sparked by a trip through Europe, and when he returned he sought to educate himself and find others to experiment with him; he saw a sign in a natural food store advertising a “Homebrewing Class," so he tried it out. Around this same time he took a trip to the USDA hop research farm because he wanted to grow his own; this interest soon became a real job, and he sold his first hops through his company Freshops in 1982. He and Jerry Bockmore took over the management of Oregon Trail Brewing in 1993, a brewery that opened in downtown Corvallis in 1987 and closed briefly in 1992.
Ralph Woodall works in sales for Yakima-Chief Hopunion, a company he has been with since the mid-1980s. Woodall was raised in the Yakima Valley, and most of his professional career has been in the hop industry. He travelled extensively for his job, attending many festivals, trade shows, and other events. He was also active in the Master Brewers Association of America. Tom Carpenter is a fourth generation hop grower based in Granger, Washington. Carpenter's family has deep roots in the Valley; Carpenter Ranches was established in 1868 when Charles Carpenter left his hop growing family in New York to settle in the Ahtanum area of the Yakima Valley. Theirs was the first hop farm in Washington State east of the Cascade Mountains, which is now the largest hop producing region in the world. Tom Carpenter started growing hops when he was 12, selling them by the pound to his father; he has been growing the crop ever since. Later in his professional career he helped form the grower cooperative that eventually became the Yakima Chief hop company. Carpenter is largely retired now, and his children and grandchildren continue to expend their family operations.
Aaron Sarnoff-Wood is one of the co-founders of 2 Towns Ciderhouse in Corvallis, Oregon. Sarnoff-Wood was born in Riverside, California, where he lived for five years. In 1986 his family initially moved to Albany, but after nine months relocated to Corvallis, where Sarnoff-Wood lived until graduating from Crescent Valley High School. As a child he played soccer, had interests in sciences like field biology, and found opportunities to explore both art and graphic design. He moved to Eugene in 1999 and lived near campus, in a rundown house a couple of blocks away from where Animal House was filmed; it was in the basement of that house that he began his home brewing experiments. While at the University of Oregon Sarnoff-Wood studied Graphic Design and also worked at an independently-owned video store. After college he took a position doing design for InterVision Media, but was laid off in 2007 and began to consider a career change. He and friends Dave Takush and Lee Larsen started 2 Towns Ciderhouse in 2010.
Gary and Susan Wyatt are the founders and owners of Tumalo Hops, a farm near Bend in Central Oregon. Susan was born in Bend, and Gary was born in Reno, Nevada. They married in 1973 and moved to Tumalo in 1978. Susan stayed home with their children, but took a position at brokerage house and construction company after they were in school; she worked there until the business closed in 2008. Gary was in the Navy during Vietnam, and after his second tour he left the service. He began work at a sawmill and was laid off when the mill closed in 1992; he learned how to do carpentry, glassmaking, and electrical work. The Wyatts chose to utilize five acres of their land to grow hops, planting, cultivating, and harvesting everything by hand starting in 2008.
Veronica Vega is a Brewmaster at Deschutes Brewery, focusing on research and development. Vega grew up in Southern California, where her family had an avocado orchard. She came from a big family, and her early life was full of good food and lots of work on the farm. She moved to Northern California to attend Humboldt State University and study Botany; she wanted to be in the forest, so she chose that school because it was the farthest north without paying out of state tuition. She worked briefly in the forest service before moving to Bend. In 2006, she took a position with Deschutes Brewery as a tour guide, moving up to cellar work, production brewing, and lead brewer at the downtown pub. In 2015, she was promoted to one of the top brewer positions.
Oregon State University--Faculty.
Born digital.; Oral histories (document genres)
Agricultural chemistry--Oregon.; Agriculture--Oregon.; Beer--Oregon--Portland--History.; Beer--United States.; Brewing industry--Oregon.; Hops--Harvesting--Oregon.; Hops--Oregon.; Microbreweries--United States.; Women brewers--Oregon.
Agriculture; Businesses and Corporations; Colleges and Universities; Women; Oregon; Electronic Records; Oral Histories
All interviews were conducted by OSU Libraries Special Collections & Archives Research Center staff or colleagues as indicated.
Future additions to this collection are anticipated.
Collection is open for research. Access to the John Harris audio file is available on site only.
The Oregon Hops and Brewing Archives Oral History Collection is complemented by several other collections. The Brewing and Fermentation Collection (MSS BFRC) consists of materials collected by the OSU Special Collections and Archives Research Center pertaining to the history, growth, and culture of the Pacific Northwest brewing industry, including regional hops and barley farming, commercial craft and home brewing, and craft cider and mead.
Additional materials related Oregon State University research and manuscript collections are detailed on the Oregon Hops and Brewing Archives library research guide. More information pertaining to the history of hop growing and brewing in Oregon can be found on the Oregon Hops and Brewing Archives website.
The Larry Sidor, Jeff Edgerton, and Theodore Cox interviews have also been described in the Oregon State University Sesquicentennial Oral History Project.
All interviews described in this collection are available online. Born digital .mpg or .mp3 files created in the building of this collection are also available on site.
Interviews are arranged chronologically by date of interview.
The Oregon Hops and Brewing Archives Oral History Collection is a growing repository of interviews with industry professionals, journalists and community members.
The collection is entirely born digital. Interviews led by project staff are captured using either video and audio recorders (sometimes both), and the resulting raw .mts files (almost always multiple files per interview) and .wav files constitute the original materials described in this collection. These raw files are stored on the libraries preservation server, as are lower-resolution derivative .mpg files that represent the full length of represent the full length of certain interview videos. In addition, .mp3 copies of each interview file have been generated from the raw files and are stored on the Special Collections and Archives Research Center (SCARC) file server for local access. Online copies of each interview video are likewise available in two locations: as lightly described video files accessible through OSU's MediaSpace media distribution platform and on the OHBA Research Guide.
Most interviews have been indexed with time-stamps or are in the process of being transcribed. Unless otherwise stated, all interviews are available for streaming online.
Materials assembled in the process of developing interview topics and permissions forms signed by interview subjects are held in the SCARC central files.
- Interviews, 2014; Series 1
  - Ockert, Carole, March 1, 2014
    Carole Ockert describes the “brewing adventure” she and her husband, renowned brewer Karl Ockert, have shared, from the European backpacking trip of their youth to the extensive success of BridgePort Brewing Company. Ockert also discusses the sense of community and camaraderie that surrounded the first few Portland brewers of the 1980s. As BridgePort and its neighbors experienced growth, so too did the community’s relationships, purpose, and goals. The interview was conducted by Tiah Edmunson-Morton on March 1, 2014 at the residence of Carole and Karl Ockert in Lake Oswego, Oregon.
  - Crosby, Blake, March 7, 2014
    A fifth-generation hop grower, Blake Crosby owns and operates Crosby Hop Farm in Woodburn, Oregon with his father, Kevin. Since 1900, the Crosby family has grown a variety of aromatic and bittering hops on their land. In this interview, Crosby traces the trajectory of his family’s farming and business practices. Crosby also discusses his personal connection to hop growing and his interest in the changing dynamics of the craft brew-driven industry in Oregon. Crosby believes the industry’s new focus on quality and stewardship has helped bridge the urban-rural divide between consumers and growers. The interview was conducted by Tiah Edmunson-Morton on March 7, 2014 on location at Crosby Hop Farm in Woodburn, Oregon.
  - Foyston, John, March 28, 2014
    John Foyston, former Oregonian beer columnist, shares his personal history in this interview, describing events that led him to write about Oregon’s emergent beer culture. Foyston recounts his time studying journalism at the University of Oregon, as well as the importance of influences like the Vietnam War and music upon his career path. After owning a motorcycle shop, Foyston was an Arts and Entertainment freelance journalist, tracking the immense growth and changes of the Portland craft beer industry. The interview was conducted by Peter Kopp, Tiah Edmunson-Morton, and Tim Hills on March 28, 2014 in Portland, Oregon.
  - Aney, Warren, April 4, 2014
    Warren Aney is alum of Oregon State University who received his Master’s degree in the 1970s. He went on to work as a wildlife ecologist. Aney met Charles Coury when he moved to Oregon due to their mutual interest in wine. He joined Coury’s wine association as a non-grower member. There Aney helped run their winery tours. He also took Coury’s viticulture class at PCC in 1972-3. Aney was at the dedication of the Cartwright Brewery. When he and his family moved back to Portland in the early 1990s where he started working for a travel agency leading wine tours. Aney has written a paper accepted by the Ecological Society on Oregon’s wine climates in 1974. Warren Aney is also a wine enthusiast, and in his interview talks about his friendship with Charles Coury, brewer and proprietor of the short-lived Cartwright Brewing in Portland, Oregon. This interview was conducted by Tiah Edmunson-Morton and Korey Jackson on April 4, 2014 at Aney's home in Portland, Oregon.
  - Fahrendorf, Teri, April 19, 2014
    One of the first female brewers in the modern history of the Pacific Northwest, Teri Fahrendorf is internationally recognized for her success in brewing and her educational, networking efforts. In this interview, Fahrendorf describes her first forays into brewing, including an injury which pushed her northward from the Golden Gate and Triple Rock breweries of California to Steelhead Brewing in Eugene, Oregon. The interview discusses Fahrendorf’s later “road brew” trip in depth—an adventure which led to the creation of women-driven projects like the Pink Boots Society, Barley’s Angels and International Women’s Collaboration Brew Day. Throughout the narrative, Fahrendorf stresses the importance of education and art in the brewing industry, both past and present. The interview was conducted by Tiah Edmunson-Morton on April 19, 2014 at Occidental Brewing Company in Portland, Oregon. Portions of the interview were used in the documentary history project “OHBA Stories.”
  - Townsend, Shaun, May 7, 2014
    Dr. Shaun Townsend is the senior researcher leading Oregon State University’s Aroma Hop Breeding Program. The project, sponsored in conjunction with Indie Hops, focuses on developing experimental hop varieties which grow best in Oregon and contain aromatic properties conducive to craft brewing. In this interview, Townsend recalls the catalysts and challenges behind the program, as well as the scientific and physical processes involved in its maintenance. Townsend also discusses his role as an informational liaison to the general public in the absence of a hop-focused extension agent. Interview conducted at the OSU Experimental Hop Yard, Hwy 34, Corvallis, OR. Portions of the footage were used in the documentary history project “OHBA Stories.”
  - Shellhammer, Thomas, May 7, 2014
    Thomas Shellhammer is the Nor’Wester Professor of Fermentation Science at OSU, where he runs a lab dedicated to the chemical and sensory analysis of hops. With his guidance, undergraduate and graduate students alike receive hands-on experience in the brewing process. In this interview, Shellhammer discusses his own path to research, as well as the trajectory of OSU’s Fermentation Science program within the Department of Food Science & Technology. Shellhammer also discusses aspects of the program related to funding and local collaborations. The interview was conducted by Tiah Edmunson-Morton on May 7, 2014 at the brewing facilities in OSU’s Wiegand Hall in Corvallis, Oregon. Interview conducted at Wiegand Hall, OSU, Corvallis, OR by Tiah Edmunson-Morton. Portions of the footage were used in the documentary history project “OHBA Stories.”
  - Crosby, Blake, May 16, 2014
    A fifth-generation hop grower, Blake Crosby owns and operates Crosby Hop Farm in Woodburn, Oregon with his father, Kevin. Since 1900, the Crosby family has grown a variety of aromatic and bittering hops. In this interview, Crosby briefly discusses the history of his family's farm before focusing on more recent changes wrought by the increasing demand of hops for craft brewing. Crosby also discusses potential market trajectories, as well as the importance of preserving agricultural history for future generations. The video concludes with a tour of the farm's pelletizer, the only machine of its kind on an Oregon farm at the time of production. The interview was conducted by Tiah Edmunson-Morton and Korey Jackson on May 16, 2014 on location at Crosby Farms in Woodburn, Oregon. Portions of the footage were used in the documentary history project “OHBA Stories.”
  - Goschie, Gayle, May 16, 2014
    Gayle Goschie is a third-generation hop grower and co-owner of Goschie Farms in Silverton, Oregon. She and her two brothers, Gordon and Glenn, grow hops, grapes, and other crops on land her family has cultivated for more than 100 years. In this interview, Goschie talks about the history of her family's farm and the changes that have occurred in hop growing practices due to technological advancements and economic trends. Goschie also addresses the value of a steady, loyal employee base, as well as the advent of the sustainable farming practices Goschie Farms is so recognized for. The interview was conducted by Tiah Edmunson-Morton on May 16, 2014 on location at Goschie Farms. Portions of the footage were used in the documentary history project “OHBA Stories.”
  - Widmer, Kurt and Rob, May 10, 2014
    Rob and Kurt Widmer are the founders of one of Oregon’s most recognizable breweries, Widmer Brothers Brewing. Based out of Portland, Oregon, the brothers’ brewery helped serve as a catalyst for the Pacific Northwest craft brew revolution. In this interview, the Widmers discuss their past and current relationships with regional brewers and the local community, crediting Portland’s pioneer heritage and adventurous drinking culture as keys to their success. The brothers also discuss pieces of their business model, which helped them weather challenges inherent to the industry. The interview was conducted by Tiah Edmunson-Morton on May 10, 2014 at the Widmer Brothers Gasthaus Pub in Portland, Oregon. The video concludes with the filming of a tasting session. Portions of the footage were used in the documentary history project “OHBA Stories.”
  - Eckhardt, Fred, July 23, 2014
    Fred Eckhardt was a prominent beer writer and critic whose work includes seminal brewing texts like A Treatise on Lager Beer and The Essentials of Beer Style. In this interview, he describes the events of his early life, recounting his time spent in a children’s home in Washington and his years as a U.S. Marine. Upon moving to Portland, Eckhardt became deeply involved with the burgeoning homebrewing and craft brewing movements—environments which he describes in depth in this interview. Eckhardt also offers information about early Pacific Northwest breweries like Olympia, Red Hook, Widmer Brothers, and McMenamins. This interview was conducted by Tiah Edmunson-Morton, Tim Hills, and John Foyston on July 23, 2014 in Portland, Oregon.
  - Nickerson, Gail, August 6, 2014
    Gail Nickerson is a former chemist with the Department of Agriculture at Oregon State University, whose work was immensely influential in the global hop industry. In this interview, Nickerson discusses the series of event which led her to work in the research lab of USDA chemist Sam Likens. Nickerson discusses her move from dishwasher to published researcher, recounting the technology and methods utilized and developed by her research team. Of particular interest are Nickerson’s descriptions of hop analysis and the engineering of varieties with researcher Al Haunold. The interview was conducted by Peter Kopp and Tiah Edmunson-Morton on August 6, 2014 in Corvallis, Oregon.
  - Weathers, Don, September 24, 2014
    Don Weathers is a second-generation hop grower in the Willamette Valley, having owned and operated several farms throughout the state, many of which are now run by his children and grandchildren. In this interview, Weathers and his wife, Rosalie, recount the early years of their childhoods and marriage. The couple discusses post-World War II farming practices, as well as the changes to hop cultivation brought by increased mechanization. Weathers also briefly recounts the emergence of organizations like the Oregon Hop Commission and joint suppliers like Yakima Chief-Hopunion. The interview was conducted by Tiah Edmunson-Morton on September 24, 2014 in the couple’s home in Keizer, Oregon.
  - Townsend, Shaun, November 3, 2014